The new morning we've finally found
やっと見つけた　新しい朝は
Yatto mitsuketa atarashii asa wa
is being hampered by the past.
月日が邪魔をする
Tsukihi ga jama wo suru
What we chased after wasn't the future,
向かう先は　「次」じゃなくて
Mukau saki wa tsugi ja nakute
but the past so full of remorse.
「過」ばかり追いかけた
Sugi bakari oikaketa
The ruthless memories won't stop playing;
鳴り止まない　容赦ない思い出たちは
Nariyamanai yousha nai omoide tachi wa
they won't be forgiving us for a long time.
許してくれそうにもない
Yurushite kuresou nimonai
It's about now that a teardrop
そろそろかな　手探り　疲れた頬を
Sorosoro kana tesaguri tsukareta hoho wo
beings to roll down my fatigued cheeks.
葛藤がこぼれ落ちる
Kattou ga koboreochiru
Will this rain ever stop?
雨は　いつか止むのでしょうか
Ame wa itsuka yamunodeshouka
I've been freezing for a long time.
ずいぶん長い間　冷たい
Zuibun nagai aida tsumetai
Why does the rain continue to fix on me?
雨は　どうして僕を選ぶの
Ame wa doushite boku wo erabuno
I wonder if it could embrace me.
包まれて　いいかな
Tsutsumarete iikana
Today, the rain falls again;
雨は　止むことを知らずに
Ame wa yamu koto wo shirazuni
endlessly it falls knowing no end.
今日も降り続くけれど
Kyou mo furitsuzukukeredo
We nestle close to each other to share the warmth
そっと　差し出した傘の中で
Sotto sashidashita kasa no naka de
under this umbrella, you gently held out to me.
温もりに　寄り添いながら
Nukumori ni yorisoinagara
Calm down...
落ち着いて…
I want to talk to you...
オレは君と話がしたい…
Please, just listen to me...
とにかく話を聞いてくれ…
And you too, talk to me...
そして君も話してくれ…
Yes... that's right...
そう…そうだ
You're... not alone...
君は一人じゃない…
Golden hair...
金の髪…西から来たのか
He must have come from the west.
Well, we should at least bury him.
どれ　埋葬だけでもしてやるか
He's alive!
生きてるよ
You're kidding me!
うそだろ
Get yourself together!
しっかりしろ
Hey, are you all right?!
大丈夫か
Water! Bring him some water!
水だ　水を持ってこい
Don't drink it in one gulp. Take it slow.
一気に飲むなよ　少～しずつだ
Can you understand our language?
言葉は分かるか
We're merchants from Xing.
私たちはシンの商人だ
Where were you headed?
どこに行くつもりだったんだ
I have nowhere to return to...
帰る所がない…行く所もない…
I also have nowhere to go...
I was afraid of staying in Xerxes, so I ran...
クセルクセスにいるのが怖くて
逃げた…
You're right...
だよな…
I'm sorry...
すまない
I couldn't stop him...
オレが止められなかった…
I'm sorry...!
すまない…
I'm sorry, Sergence...!
すまない　サージェンス…
Sergence was a master carpenter.
大工の棟梁だったサージェンス
He often came to the palace for repairs.
宮殿修理によく来ていた  覚えてるか
Remember him?
And his son, Dozle, looked up to his father and worked hard in order to succeed him.
その息子ドズルは父親を尊敬し
後を継ごうと頑張っていた
And Caiya, the florist girl.
花屋の娘カイヤ
She was kind and thoughtful.
優しくて思いやりのある子だ
Sari, the horse owner, really loved to drink.
馬飼いのサリは大層な酒好きだ
We got along well.
オレと話が合う
Little boy Tommy's dream was to become a scholar.
タミィ少年の夢は学者になることだった
Gidalush was a chef.
ギダルーシュは料理人
He once got fired for giving a free meal to a traveler with no money.
金のない旅人にタダで飯を食わせて
クビになったことがある
Andal, a fellow slave,
奴隷仲間のアンダルは
主人にうまく取り入ったオレを
hated me for gaining the master's favor.
目の敵にしていたなぁ
Zul was a hopeless villain and was only awaiting his execution,
ズールはどうにもならん極悪人で
死刑を待つ身だったが
but he apparently wants to get back at you before that.
最後にお前に一矢報いたいそうだ
Get back at me?
一矢報いるだと
Those are the souls that just infiltrated your body.
今お前の中に侵入した魂たちだよ
They're cooperating with me for the sole purpose of defeating you.
お前を倒すという
ただ一つの目的のために
オレに協力してくれている
You're saying that the philosopher's stone is working together with you, each one retaining its own will?
賢者の石が個々に意思を持って
協力しているだと
When they're nothing but an energy form?
ただのエネルギー体が
Do you think it's impossible?
ありえん…と思うか
It almost drove me nuts to deal with these crazed souls one by one.
確かに荒ぶる魂
一人一人を相手にするのは
気が狂いそうだったよ
But I had plenty of time to talk to them.
だが　こいつらと対話する時間は
たっぷりあった
Thanks to this immortal body you gave me.
お前のくれた
この死ねない体のお陰でな
You talked to them?
対話をしただと
That's right.
そう
And that's precisely what you didn't do.
それこそお前がしなかったこと
I've already spoken to every single one of the 536329 people inside me.
オレは自分の中にいる
53万6329人全員と対話を終えている
D-Damn you...!
おっ…おのれ…
Go back to where you came from,
生まれたところに帰るんだ
Dwarf in the Flask, Homunculus.
フラスコの中の小人
ホムンクルスよ
Sorry, but I'm going to be destroying your container.
悪いが入れ物を壊させてもらう
Tearing apart your skin is the same thing as breaking your flask.
皮袋が破ければ
フラスコが壊れたも同じ
You'll turn into dust.
お前は塵になる
Experience the will of the ones you looked down on.
お前が見下したものたちの思いを知れ
Aren't you the one who's looking down on someone, Hohenheim?
見下しているのは
そちらの方ではないか
ホーエンハイムよ
You can survive even after abandoning your skin?
皮を捨てても生きていけるのか
Don't think for a moment that you fools are the only ones who progressed.
進歩してるのは
自分たちだけだと思うなよ
Didn't I tell you that I'll become a perfect being?
完全な存在になると言っただろう
What?!
なんだと
A frontal attack?!
正面から
Why must I enter my own castle through the back door?
自分の城に入るのに
裏口から入らねばならぬ理由があるのかね
Infantry, retreat!
歩兵　下がれ
Impossible!
バカな
Did we get him?!
やったか
Take over the steering!
操縦　代われ
Y-Yes sir!
はっ　はい
Dammit!
くそ～どこだ
Where are you?!
Damn you...
野郎　戦車をたった一人で…
You took down a tank by yourself?!
Captain!
大尉
Captain Buccaneer!
バッカニア大尉
What's the matter?
どうした　主が帰ったのだぞ
The master has returned.
Open the gate.
門を開けたまえ
Open the gate, Falman.
開けたまえ　ファルマン君
I'm sorry, Colonel Mustang...
すみません　マスタング大佐…
This may become my grave...
オレ　ここで死ぬかも…
Hey, hey.
Stop trying to act cool with a lame face like that.
情けない面で
カッコつけてんじゃねぇ
If it's about manliness, I can't lose to anyone either.
男の意地なら
こっちも負けてられねぇんだよ
I can still fight!
オレはまだ戦えるぞ
Rubbish.
くだらん
This is what people call 'recklessness'.
人はそれを蛮勇と呼ぶのだよ
Exactly.
そのとおり
Letting your passions run wild and barking won't get you far at all.
激情に任せて吠えたところで
得なことなんてありゃしねぇ
But for some reason...
だけどなんでかねぇ
I can't bring myself to abandon people like that.
そういうの見捨てる気持ちに
なれねぇんだよなぁ
Dammit!
くそ～大総統が戻ってきた途端
They've started to make a comeback now that the Führer President has returned!
盛り返してきやがった
ここを抜かれたら正門を取られる
If they get past this place, they'll take back the main gate!
なんとしても持ちこたえろ
Hold out no matter what!
Yes.
はい　はい　本当ですか
What?!
Are you serious?!
Madam Bradley!
ブラッドレイ夫人
大総統閣下は無事です
The Führer President is fine!
生きておられます
He's alive!
I'm so glad...
よかった
Are you okay?
大丈夫ですか
Yes, I'm fine.
私は大丈夫です
I'm so glad...
よかった  あの人が生きていてくれた
He's alive...
Is he hurt?!
ケガはしていないのですか
I don't have the details on that yet.
それはまだ分かりません
All I know is that he's wiping out the Briggs soldiers at Central Headquarters.
閣下は中央司令部にて
ブリッグズ兵を掃討中とのことです
Should we blame it on Briggs?
ブリッグズになすりつけるか
でも…
But...!
It's to protect Colonel Mustang.
マスタング大佐を守るためだ
Yeah.
For starters, it's great news that the Führer President is safe.
まずは閣下が無事で何よりです
Yes.
I just hope Selim is safe and sound as well...
セリムも無事ならいいのですけど
If he's fighting against the Briggs soldiers,
ブリッグズ兵と戦っているということは
it must mean that Major General Armstrong is the mastermind behind the coup d'etat.
アームストロング少将が
クーデターの首謀者のようですね
Armstrong?
アームストロング
Oh...
The female general who came to Central a little while ago.
少し前にセントラルに来た女将軍だね
Now the real problem is, how much of the upper echelon is involved?
問題はどれくらい
上層部が巻き込まれているか
ということです
So he was alive...
生きてましたか
We can't underestimate a Homunculus, after all.
さすが人造人間…というところですか
The fact that we pretended to be on the
Führer President's side came back to haunt us.
大総統の側に付いた振りをしたのが
裏目に出たわね
We had to make Major General Armstrong out to be the villain...
アームストロング少将を
悪者にしなきゃならないなんて…
This place is getting dangerous as well.
ここも危なくなってきましたね
Yeah.
そうね
I wonder what's going to happen to us.
僕たち　どうなるんでしょう
I don't know.
分からないわ
We've said that we're on the Führer President's side,
一応大総統側の人間だと主張してるから
so I doubt they'll fire at us so easily.
向こうもそう簡単に
攻撃してこないでしょうけど
But what if Bradley comes back into full control again?
ブラッドレイが全権を掌握し直したら…
We'll probably get crushed like ants.
すぐにつぶされるかもね
Even if the madam is here?!
夫人がいてもですか
Do you honestly think they're that compassionate?
連中にそんな情があると思う
It's been a while.
久しぶりだな
You should have just run off somewhere after that.
あのまま黙って
逃げておればよかったものを
Unfortunately, I'm as greedy as can be.
あいにく　底なしの強欲なんでねぇ
お前の命も欲しいんだよ　ラース
I want your life too, Wrath.
Reinforcements... I'm assuming?
援軍…なのか
Everyone in town was saying that you died in a train wreck.
列車事故で死んだって
町中の噂になってたぜ
How did you survive?
どうやって生き残った
My eyes are too keen.
目がよすぎるのでな
It only takes a moment to decide the route I need to take to escape through the rubble.
がれきの中のどこをどう走れば
逃げられるのか
一瞬で判断できるのだよ
But I really am getting old.
しかし　やはり年だな
My body can't handle things as well as it could back then.
昔ほど体がついてこんわ
He can do all this even if his body isn't at its peak?
身体能力がピークじゃないのにこれかよ
Lin Yao... right?
リン·ヤオ…だな
Wow!
I haven't seen you since you let me stay in your beat-up apartment!
ボロアパートにかくまってもらって以来かな
It's been a while, Warrant Officer Falman.
久しぶりだねぇ　ファルマン准尉
少尉だ
I'm a Second Lieutenant now!
あなたには一宿一飯の恩がある
I owe you for a night's lodging and a meal.
Let me lend you a hand.
ちょっと手伝うよ…
He said that, but both of us are actually just doing this for ourselves!
とか言って
ほんとはオレもこいつも
個人的なこだわりなんだけどな
Trying to get into my blind spot?
私の死角に入るか
中の相棒にお前との戦い方を
My partner inside me taught me how to fight you.
教えてもらったんでねぇ
I see.
そうかね
Then I'll do this.
ならばこうだ
He's starting to get pushed back.
押されだしたぞ
やばいんじゃないか
Isn't this looking bad for him?
Fire! Fire!
撃て撃て　撃て～
Shoot!
Idiots! Don't interfere!
アホ　手ぇ出すな
D-Damn you!!
おっ　おのれぇ～
Captain!
大尉
Seems like you have a sturdy set of abs.
丈夫な腹筋だな
Now you won't be able to use your sword.
これで得意の剣術は使えまい
Don't be reckless, moron!
ムチャすんな 　バカ野郎　だが
But...!
Good job!
よくやった
Christ...
やれやれだ
I'm not too used to wielding these weapons.
この手の武器は
使い慣れていないのだがね
Not bad, old man.
やってくれるなぁ　おっさん
The Führer President has returned?
閣下が戻られたと
Yes, sir.
はい　正体不明の男と
He's currently engaged in combat with an unidentified man.
戦闘中であります
We're going to gather more men, wipe out the small fries from Briggs,
直ちに兵力を投入して
ブリッグズの雑魚どもを蹴散らし
and rescue the Führer President.
大総統をお救いする
Replenish weapons and fill in vacancies.
武器　欠員を補充
Regain the main gate.
正門を奪還せよ
Yes, sir!
Go! Go! Go!
This is bad!
やばい
The Central Soldiers have gotten back up!
中央兵が息を吹き返した
My bad!
すまん　こいつの相手で
I've already got my hands full with him!
手いっぱいだ
I'm leaving the rest to you guys!
そっちは頼むわ
What?!
What are we supposed to do when they have so many more men than us?!
頼むったって
この兵力差でどうしろってんだ
どうにかしろ
Figure something out!
"Figure something out"?
どうにかしろって…
Captain! Hang in there!
(大尉　しっかり)
We'll have to do just that...
やるしかないか…
Hey!
You all carry Captain Buccaneer somewhere safe!
お前たちはバッカニア大尉を
安全な場所に運べ
Roger!
はい
We're going to move that.
それ　動かすぞ
Roger!
はい
Dammit! We're being held back by two machine guns?!
くそっ　たかだか２丁の機関銃に
足止めをくらうとは
Since they have the high ground, we're at a disadvantage!
この高低差は不利だ
Can we get in contact with any of the squadrons in headquarters?
連絡の取れる隊は中にいるか
Have them open the gate from the inside.
中から門をこじあけさせろ
Roger!
はっ
This is the 3rd Guards Battalion!
こちら　第３近衛大隊
Central Headquarters Garrison, answer!
中央司令部守備隊　応答せよ
(人形兵がまだ東門に…)
There are still dolls at the east gate...
What?
なんだ　何を言ってるんだ
What are they saying?
Give me that.
貸せ
I'm Gamelan from the Guards Battalion.
近衛隊のガムランだ
We're at the front gate.
こちらは正面ゲートにいる
Can you not open the gate to headquarters from the inside?
内部から司令部の門は開けられないのか
It's impossible!
無理です　人形兵たちがいて
There are dolls lurking about, so we can't open the gate!
門は開けられません
Dolls?
人形兵　なんのことだ
What are you talking about?
What happened?!
どうした　何が起きてる
What's going on?!
なんだ　新手か
What?!
More enemies?!
What on earth is going on down there?
下で　一体何が起きてるんだ…
Oh?
Not bad, gramps.
やるなぁ　じいさん
Thanks. You saved me.
サンキュー　助かったぜ
I didn't save you. I saved the young master's body.
貴様を助けたのではない
若の体を助けたのだ
If you say so.
あらそう
Releasing a nasty aura from the young master's body...
若の体で気色悪い気を放ちおって
Well, I couldn't have found you otherwise.
まあ　だからこそ見つけられたのだがな
So, who's this guy who's left unscathed despite our combined efforts?
で　わしや貴様の腕をもってしても
傷一つ付けることのできぬ
こやつはなんだ
King Bradley.
キング·ブラッドレイだよ
Oh.
It's my first time seeing him with my own eyes.
生で見るのは初めてだわい
So he's the one who ripped off my granddaughter's arm...!
こやつが  我が孫娘の腕をちぎりよった男か
Ever since that day passed,
あの日からずっと
Ano hi kara zutto
I promised myself that I'd never cry.
泣かないと決めてきたけど
Nakanaito kimetekitakedo
But even while I hoarded up the pain,
痛みを重ねても
Itami wo kasanetemo
there was something I couldn't forgive myself for.
何かを許せずにいた
Nanika wo yurusezu ni ita
I'll never be able
もう戻れない
Mou modorenai
to return to those days.
いくつもの日々
Ikutsumo no hibi
I'm still powerless.
僕はまだ何もできずに
Boku wa mada nanimo dekizuni
I watch as the shards of memories disappear, one by one;
君のいた記憶の破片
Kimi no ita kioku no kakera
memories of when you were still with me.
またひとつ 消えてゆく
Mata hitotsu kieteyuku
I long to become
今日よりもっと
Kyou yori motto
stronger than I am now,
強くなりたい
Tsuyoku naritai
so that my voice will eventually reach you.
この声がいつか届くように
Kono koe ga itsuka todokuyouni
If the wind happens to stop
歩き続けて
Arukitsuzukete
in the midst of my long journey,
風が止んだら
Kaze ga yandara
I'll look up at the sky in search of you.
君を探して空見上げるよ
Kimi wo sagashite sora miageruyo
Beyond the daybreak, a ray of light breaks free.
夜明けの先に光がさすよ
Yoake no saki ni hikari ga sasuyo
A rainbow spans across the sky.
虹がかかるよ
Niji ga kakaruyo
次回　鋼の錬金術師
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
When a man knows the enemy, and knows himself,
Fullmetal  Alchemist
he realizes the end of the battle.
第５７話　『永遠の暇』
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
However, he will not die for nothing.
さらば　我が主
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
Episode 57, Eternal Leave.
Farewell, my lord.
I shall watch over you from the other side.